Guide to the Library Shelving Facility, Yale University, Construction Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Library Shelving Facility, Yale University, construction records
1998-1999
RU 860
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2.25
The records consist of photographs and their negatives of the site for and construction of the Yale University Library Shelving Facility (LSF) in 1998 and an exhibit materials from exhibit titled "Library Shelving Facility".
Yale University. Library
General note
Forms part of Yale Record Group 32-A (YRG 32-A), Central records of the Yale University Library and records of the librarian.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arrangement
The records are arranged by accession.
Scope and Contents
The records consist of photographs and their negatives of the site for and construction of the Yale University Library Shelving Facility (LSF) in 1998 and an exhibit materials from exhibit titled "Library Shelving Facility".
Academic libraries; Library storage centers; Photographs; Yale University. Library
- Photographs of the construction of the Library Shelving Facility, 1998; Accession 2001-A-111
  - Negatives, 1998 (Box 1)
  - Binder of photographs taken of the Hamden building site and construction of the facility (1 of 2), 1998 February - November (Box 2)
  - Binder of photographs taken of the Hamden building site and construction of the facility (2 of 2), 1998 February - November (Box 3)
- Exhibit materials on the Library Shelving Facility, 1999; Accession 2001-A-170
  Scope and Contents
  The photographs in this exhibit were chosen to document points in time that best illustrate the nature of the work to provide an environment capable of prolonging the life of materials considered at risk, for which Yale University has constructed a state of the art, high efficiency library shelving facility in Hamden, Connecticut. Since operations began in November 1998, a variety of infrequently used materials have been transferred to the new off-campus site: books, films, video tapes, and archival materials are now shelved by size on modular shelving soaring thirty feet high in a rigorously controlled environment.
  The exhibit highlights the construction of the Library Shelving Facility and provide an overview of its operation.
  - 1. Shelving facility in Hamden, Connecticut. (Box 1)
  - 2. An excellent building lot, over six acres in size is procured for the construction of the Library Shelving Facility. (Box 1)
  - 3. Worker in a hole, ready to pour cement. (Box 1)
  - 4. One of the first steps in preparing the site is to install storm drains to accommodate surface water. (Box 1)
  - 5. Footings are poured to support the structure. (Box 1)
  - 6. Until the roof is install, temporary steel beams support the walls. (Box 1)
  - 7. The entrance to the processing area begins to take shape. (Box 1)
  - 8. The roof structure is installed using both a cherry picker and manual labor. (Box 1)
  - 9. The interior of the shelving module comes together as the roof is completed. (Box 1)
  - 10. Scaffolding is used to construct the exterior walls, while a crane loads roofing materials. (Box 1)
  - 11. Roof ballast is shoveled on the roof to secure the roof membrane. (Box 1)
  - 12. An asphalt-laying machine is used to create the driveway. (Box 1)
  - 13. Inside view of the partial finished structure. (Box 1)
  - 14. The super flat slab is poured to a zero-degree tolerance. This is a critical step in preparing the foundation for the thirty-foot shelving units. (Box 1)
  - 15. A closer view of the super flat slab. (Box 1)
  - 16. Ductwork to supply conditioned air to the module is installed in the ceiling, as are high-pressure sodium lights. (Box 1)
  - 17. Refrigeration-type panels are installed on the interior walls of the shelving module. (Box 1)
  - 18. The mechanical system, which controls the environment, is delivered in one piece. (Box 1)
  - 19. Chris Fiorillo [Delivery Assistant] cleans books upon arrival at our innovative cleaning station. (Box 1)
  - 20. Hans Kirsch [Delivery Assistant] wraps items needing extra protection. Books are wrapped to protect both the Library Shelving Facility environment and valuable bindings. (Box 1)
  - 21. Marvin Tillman unloads materials from campus that were transported in special protective bins. (Box 1)
  - 22. Jim Sposito [Delivery Assistant] illustrates the use of a template to size materials before placing them into appropriate trays. (Box 1)
  - 23. Tanya Grant-Lopes [Delivery Assistant] enter barcodes into the inventory system as part of the accessioning process. (Box 1)
  - 24. Ladders for the thirty-foot high shelving units are installed with six aisles. (Box 1)
  - 25. Hans Kirsch [Delivery Assistant] lifts a truckload of items to shelve in the module. (Box 1)
  - 26. Copy of the Eli Express form, which may be found at url: http://www.library.yale.edu/circ/eliexprs.html (Box 1)